<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jones of Hatton-Garden, two doors from the sign of the New-Hole in the Wall, his book of cures</title>
            <author>Jones, of Hatton-Garden.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J941AC</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36856</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16143965</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16143965</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47036)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1595:108)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jones of Hatton-Garden, two doors from the sign of the New-Hole in the Wall, his book of cures</title>
                  <author>Jones, of Hatton-Garden.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Advertising --  Medicine --  England.</term>
               <term>Quacks and quackery --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104840:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Jones</hi> of <hi>Hatton-Garden,</hi> two doors from the ſign of the <hi>New-hole in the wall,</hi> his Book of Cures.</head>
            <p>I ſhall not need to ſet down what Cures I can do, for there are thouſands will ſay they can do all manner of great Cures, but where have they cured any? It is not the ſaying I can or would do great Cures, but he that is known to do ſuch Cures you muſt look after, if you intend to have help, and if you pleaſe to read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this little book, you will find that there is but few Cures to be named, but what I have Cured, the Peoples names and places where they live, which are your neighbours round about you, ſo that you need not go far to know the truth of it, neither need you queſtion, but that I ſhall do the ſame Cures ſo long as it pleaſeth God to continue the bleſſing with me, and when he pleaſe to take it away I ſhall do no more.</p>
            <p>My name is <hi>Jones</hi> the Engliſh Phyſician, who through the bleſſing of God, with my own induſtry for the ſpace of twenty three years practice on the worſt of Diſtempers, have found out how to help any Diſtemper (ſo far as Curable,) and give my Books and Judgment to all for nothing.</p>
            <p>I live at a corner houſe in <hi>Hatton-Garden</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> two doors from the ſign of the <hi>New-hole in the wall,</hi> and three doors from the ſign of the <hi>Golden-ball,</hi> almoſt over againſt <hi>Baldwins, Garden-gate,</hi> at the upper corner near the ſign of the <hi>George.</hi> I have lived at this houſe two years, and as much as ſince <hi>Midſomer,</hi> this being the fourteenth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1671. and have from the date hereof, above three quarters of a year to come of my Leaſe, and when that time is expired, I intend (God willing) to go to live at my Country-houſe at <hi>Marſhfield</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter-Shire,</hi> five miles this ſide <hi>Bath,</hi> and in the mean time I will deal faithfully with you, as I have done; to the great comfort of thouſands in and about <hi>London,</hi> ſince my coming; as you may read of ſome of their names ſet down in this book, and if I do ſtay any longer than the time I have here ſet down, I will give you notice about a quarter of a year before the time is out.</p>
            <p>NOW I will tell you of ſome of the greateſt Cures that hath been done in this age, the peoples names, and places where they live, if you will diligently read over this little book; and as it is ſaid that by the mouths of two witneſſes the truth of a matter ſhall be confirmed, you have not only two witneſſes to confirm the truth of this little book, but many: inſomuch that if you will believe that there is any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uth in the world, you may believe this. I never practiſed in <hi>London</hi> before the date hereof, being from the third of <hi>June,</hi> 1669. and in this little time have done Cures as followeth, with thouſands more.</p>
            <p>I have with Gods help given help, and Cure according as it is here ſet down. I helpt the wife of Mr. <hi>Richard Subrance</hi> of <hi>Tower-hill</hi> two doors from the ſign of the <hi>Black-dog</hi> a Silk-weaver, of great pain of her Head and Stomach, ſhe being ſo weak not likely to live. The wife of Mr <hi>John Slater</hi> in <hi>Thread-needle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ally</hi> in <hi>Moor-fields,</hi> the next door to the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Shears,</hi> of deafneſs. Mr. <hi>Philip Luke</hi> of the <hi>Neathouſes</hi> of the Stone, and have it to ſhew. Mr. <hi>Ralph Swain</hi> at the <hi>Soho,</hi> almoſt over againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s-<hi>head</hi> a Carpenter, of the Ague and Feaver. The wife of Maſter <hi>Charles Parſons,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Black-raven</hi> in <hi>Perpole-lane,</hi> of a Feaver, with great pain at her Stomach. <hi>Francis Hollis</hi> in <hi>Wapping,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Water-houſe,</hi> of great pain in his Ancles, who could not get help in three or four years. Mr. <hi>John Worane</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Crooked-billet</hi> and <hi>Ship</hi> upon the <hi>Green-banck</hi> in <hi>Southwark</hi> of the Sciatica and a Feaver. Mr. <hi>William Aſh</hi> of <hi>Bednal-green</hi> over againſt the old <hi>Chappel,</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>John Weſton</hi> of the <hi>Neat-houſes</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>Nicholas White</hi> of <hi>White-hart-yard</hi> in <hi>Eaſt-ſmithfield,</hi> of the Conſumption and Cough, and Shortneſs of breath. Mr. <hi>John Davis</hi> of <hi>Pickled-herring-ſtaires,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Five-tobacco-pipes,</hi> of the Ague. Mrs. <hi>Clipſon</hi> at <hi>Saffron-hill,</hi> the next door to the <hi>Roul of Tobacco,</hi> of a Cough who could not get help by any other. The ſon of Mr. <hi>Thomas Billington</hi> a Baker in <hi>Peters-ſtreet or lane</hi> at <hi>Cow-croſs,</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Fox,</hi> of the Convulſion-fits ever ſince half a year old. Mrs. <hi>Jane Sidow</hi> at the <hi>Bank-ſide</hi> in <hi>Southwark;</hi> over againſt <hi>Hollands-leger</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Two Cats</hi> of a ſad Cough and diſtempered Stomach. Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Marland</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Key</hi> in <hi>Peters-lane</hi> near <hi>Hicks</hi>'s-<hi>hall</hi> of Deafneſs. Mrs. <hi>Mary Porter</hi> in <hi>Three-Oake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> joyning to <hi>Joneſes-lane,</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Dun-Cow</hi> near <hi>Cow-croſs,</hi> of great pain in her Legs, who could not get help in two years. Mrs. <hi>Mattha Wells</hi> of the ſame place of a ſore Leg. The wife of Mr. <hi>John
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104840:2"/>Mead</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Sugar-leaf</hi> and <hi>Two-flying-horſes</hi> in <hi>Faſhion-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Spittle-fields,</hi> of the Palſie with great Pain and Lameneſs in her Legs and Arms, with Nummedneſs, and I made her as well as ever ſhe was in her life with Gods help. Mrs. <hi>Clark</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> in <hi>Barnaby-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> of the Stone. Mr. <hi>Abel Lyon</hi> in <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> Church-yard in <hi>Barnaby-ſtreet</hi> a Feltmaker, of Deaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Fiſh,</hi> at <hi>Hodſdon</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Three Kings</hi> of great pain and lameneſs in all her Limbs, and the gripes of the Guts. I did much good to Mr. <hi>Edw. Mulanix</hi> in <hi>Long-acre</hi> in <hi>Coxes-ally,</hi> for great pain in his Stomach and Back. Mrs <hi>Mary Pain</hi> at <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lborn-conduit,</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-lyon</hi> of the Cough. The child of Mr. <hi>William Reen</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Chick-lane,</hi> of the Rickets and Feaver. Mr <hi>John Langly</hi> at the Coffe-houſe near the 3 <hi>Cranes</hi> on great <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> of a double third day Ague. <hi>Mary Moor</hi> at the <hi>Half-moon-Inn</hi> near the <hi>Kings-bench</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of Deafneſs. Mr. <hi>Henry Taylor</hi> near <hi>Shoreditch-Church</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Cradle,</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>Edward Curtis</hi> of the <hi>Neat-houſes</hi> of great pain and ſtoppage at his Stomach, he is a Gardiner. Mr. <hi>John Baker</hi> a Ship Carpenter at <hi>Deptford</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Chequer,</hi> of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, with great pain at his Side. He did much good to Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Baker</hi> the wife of the aforeſaid <hi>John Baker,</hi> for the windy Gout. Mr. <hi>Samuel Chadwell</hi> in <hi>Tully-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Horſly-down</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>VVorlds-end,</hi> of the Feaver and griping of the Guts, <hi>Southwark.</hi> Mr. <hi>John VVicks</hi> Junior, of <hi>Fig-tree-court</hi> in <hi>Barbican,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> houſe at the upper end of the Court, of the Dropſie. I did much good to Mrs <hi>Terill</hi> of the <hi>Red-lyon</hi> in <hi>VVapping</hi> (the carved <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Carver</hi> liveth over againſt it) for the Apoplexy &amp; Palſie, all one ſide; I mended her ſpeech alſo. Mr. <hi>Arthur Fowler</hi> at the three cups over againſt the May-pole in the <hi>Strand,</hi> of an Ulcer in his Bladder, who was ſo bad that he could not make one drop of water, and in ſuch torment no tongue is able to expreſs, and had the advice of many able Men, and they all or moſt of them judged it to be the Stone, but they were all miſtaken; I ſoon cauſed him to make water, and gave him eaſe of pain, and made a perfect cure in a week or a fourtnights time, with Gods help. I Cured the Child of Mr. <hi>Grimes</hi> living between <hi>Vine-ſtreet</hi> and <hi>Mutton-lane</hi> near <hi>Clarken-well</hi> a Clock-maker, of the Rickets, and Conſumption, when he was almoſt at deaths door. <hi>Elizabeth Cleverly</hi> at the <hi>VVind-mill</hi> and <hi>Three-broad-arrows</hi> in <hi>Canon-ſtreet,</hi> of the Ptiſick &amp; Cough, who was ſo bad therewith, that ſhe was likely to loſe her ſpeech. I ſaved the Leg of Mr. <hi>John Hele</hi> of <hi>Angel-alley</hi> in <hi>Biſhops- gate-ſtreet,</hi> from rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off Mr <hi>Thomas Anyon</hi> in <hi>Badford-bury</hi> over againſt the <hi>Tobacco-roul,</hi> of Looſneſs, and Vomiting, and a Cough, and Feaver, with great pain. Mr. <hi>VVilliam Stone</hi> a Seaman in <hi>VVapping</hi> near the <hi>Gun</hi>-Tavern of the Ague and Feaver. The ſon of Mr. <hi>James Bell</hi> in the <hi>Cole-yard</hi> in <hi>Drewry-lane,</hi> at the upper end of the yard, at Mr. <hi>Lawlys</hi>-houſe, of the Feaver and gripes of the Guts. <hi>William D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wſon</hi> in the Red-bull Play-houſe yard near <hi>Clarkenwell-green,</hi> of the Cough, and great pain in his Back. Mr. <hi>Samuel Jones</hi> living near the <hi>Red Lion</hi> in <hi>Gray's-Inn-lane,</hi> of the third-days Ague. Mr. <hi>Abel Bartsn</hi> at the Brew-houſe at the upper end of St. <hi>John-ſtreet,</hi> of the Gout, being near threeſcore years of age, and lay ſo lame with it, that he was not able to turn in his Bed, this being at the Fall of the Leaf, about two years ſince, &amp; he not expected to leave his Bed till the Spring; however with Gods help I made him perfectly well in a moneth or ſix weeks time. The wife of Mr. <hi>John VVilks</hi> at <hi>Pye-corner</hi> at the end of <hi>Smithfield</hi> over againſt the <hi>Blew-boot,</hi> of the Convulſion-fits, and great ſwelling and hardneſs of her Belly, which was a Tympany a breeding, and the cauſe of both theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers came with Grief. Mr. <hi>William Dyer</hi> in Half-moon-alley, without <hi>Biſhops-gate,</hi> of a ſad Ulcer in his Leg, of twelve years, and I made him well in about two months, with Gods help. <hi>Alice Baker</hi> over againſt the <hi>Black-ſwan</hi> in <hi>Turnmil-ſtreet</hi> at Mr. <hi>Corners</hi> houſe a Brick-layer, of loſneſs of her Teeth, when they were all ready to fall out of her head and made them faſt again, ſhe being near fourſcore years of age. The child of Mr. <hi>Henry Standly</hi> in <hi>Red-roſe-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Sedan</hi> of the Conſumption, when he was almoſt at deaths door. Mr. <hi>John Houſe</hi> of <hi>Bull-alley</hi> in <hi>Barnaby ſtreet Southwark,</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Moor,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Three Tuns</hi> in <hi>Petticoat-lane,</hi> a little way in <hi>Gravel-lane,</hi> of the Evil and blindneſs of one Eye, who could not get help by any other. Mr. <hi>Shepheard</hi> next door to the ſign of the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in <hi>Hatten-Garden</hi> of the New Feaver, and the Gripes of the Guts; and his tongue was as black as Ink, yet with Gods help I made him as well as ever he was in his life. The wife of Mr. <hi>Ralph Holloway</hi> at the Nags head in <hi>Gray's-Inn-lane,</hi> of a Feaver, with great weakneſs, when none thought ſhe would have lived. The wife of <hi>John Right</hi> of Brick-lane in <hi>Old-ſtreet,</hi> in Key and Swan-yard, of Deafneſs. Mr. <hi>John Michel</hi> a School-maſter in Angel-alley in <hi>Gray's-Inn-lane,</hi> of a ſore and Rheumy Eye, who had made tryal of able men for the ſpace of ſeven or eight years, and could not get any remedy, and with Gods help I made him well in nine or ten weeks. I helpt his wife alſo of great pain in her back, I helpt his Child alſo of the Chin-cough. Mr. <hi>Thomas Love</hi> near Shore-ditch Church of the Jaundies, he being above fourſcore years of age when he was cured. Mr. <hi>Richard Young</hi> of <hi>Park-ſtreet</hi> near St. <hi>Albons</hi> of a Wen on the top of his Head, who could not get help by any other in twenty years, and I took it out at twice dreſſing, not ſpilling one drop of blood. <hi>Elizabeth Brownſier</hi> of <hi>Swan-alley</hi> in the <hi>Minories,</hi> of the Convulſion fits, and ſhortneſs of Breath. <hi>Sarah Fox</hi> in <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vard</hi> in <hi>Rlachman-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Southwark.</hi> of the Ague. <hi>James George</hi> on the <hi>Bank-ſide nea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104840:2"/>the <hi>Bear-garden,</hi> in <hi>Southwark</hi> of great pain in his Shoulders, Arms, and Hips. Mr. <hi>Graves</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Blind Beggar</hi> at <hi>Cow-croſs</hi> of the Wind Gout in all his Joynts. Mr. <hi>Edward Squire,</hi> in <hi>Gowſwell-ſtreet</hi> at Mr. <hi>Matthew Brownes houſe,</hi> a Shoo-maker, over againſt the Pump between the ſign of the Maiden-head and the Bell, of a Cancered Wen in the ſide of his neck, near as bigg as a penny loafe which grew faſt to the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible or Jaw bone, and the Veins and Sinews grew through it, and I cured him without hurting the Veins and Sinews. Inſomuch that none can hardly ſee where it grew, and if he be not there now, Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> the man of the aforefaid houſe can give you an account of this great Cure. <hi>Henry Clarre</hi> of a Conſumption, when he was ſo much waſted that his fleſh was all withered away, that he had not left to cover his bones but the skin, I did never ſee any man ſo bare of fleſh, neither dead nor alive, and uſing my things he grew ſtrong and luſty, and fleſh grew up and covered his bones, in ſo much that he hath as much fleſh on his bones as any ordinary man; and this we may ſee, how God bleſſeth the means ſome times, contrary to our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation; therefore 'tis good for every one to uſe lawfull means to the very laſt; the people of the Golden Patton over againſt the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> in <hi>South-wark,</hi> will give you a full account of this great cure. The wife of Mr. <hi>Philip Pain</hi> near to St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Market</hi> over againſt the <hi>Cock</hi> and <hi>Hoop,</hi> of the Sciatica pain in her Hip being ſo bad therewith that ſhe could not take any reſt night nor day, and I helpt her of that, and alſo of the Fits of the Mother, Aged above fifty. <hi>Robert Daylly</hi> of <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames</hi> ten miles from <hi>London,</hi> of the vomiting of blood. The wife of <hi>Nicholas Biſhop,</hi> at the Sign of the Childes Coat in the <hi>Hay-market</hi> at <hi>Pickadilly,</hi> of great pain with deafneſs, noyſe, and ſinging in her Head. Mr. <hi>William Medbere</hi> of St. <hi>Martines</hi> in the Fields Coach-maker, the next door to the ſign of the Sugar-loaf at a Glaſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, of the Sciatica Gout in his hip, and at times in all his Joynts, who lay very weak, and could not get help by any of a long time, and I gave him eaſe of pain in three hours; and in a fortnights time cured him. <hi>Anne Fiſher</hi> of <hi>Church-yard Alley</hi> in <hi>Chick-lane,</hi> of deafneſs, and ſinging in the head. <hi>Heſter Wood</hi> of <hi>Church-yard Alley</hi> in <hi>Chick-lane</hi> of the ſtone in the Bladder, I took away her pain, and brought the Stone from her, in leſs than twelve hours, when ſhe was in ſuch torment that cannot be expreſt, and of great age. I have the ſtone to ſhow any that pleaſe to ſee it. The Son of Mrs. <hi>Mary Clark</hi> near the ſign of the Lamb in <hi>Iſlington,</hi> of the Lethargie, with great pain in his Head and Deafneſs. Mr. <hi>Adam Prince,</hi> at the ſign of the Boot in <hi>King-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> of the Stone and Gravel in the Kidneys and Bladder. <hi>Elizabeth Tonſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> of <hi>Newington-Buts</hi> in <hi>Blackman-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> in <hi>Lamb-Alley,</hi> of a Cancer in her Breaſt almoſt as big as a mans head, and I conſumed it away without cutting, or putting her to any pain, or hindering her buſineſs. <hi>Robert Mils</hi> of <hi>Kent-ſtreet</hi> the next door to the Roſe, <hi>Southwark,</hi> of the Ague &amp; Feaver. Mr. <hi>John Arnil</hi> at the top of <hi>Saffron-Hill</hi> of the Ague and Feaver. Mrs. <hi>Tomaſin Eſtcot</hi> of <hi>White-Croſs-ſtreet,</hi> in <hi>Bare and Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged-ſtaff-Yard,</hi> of a deafneſs with noiſe in her head. Mr. <hi>Thomas Ward</hi> of <hi>Biſhops-head-court,</hi> in <hi>Gray's-Inn-lane,</hi> of the griping pains in the Guts, and gave him preſent help; I alſo cured his daughter of a ſcald or Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie head. Mr. <hi>Gregory Coe</hi> living on the <hi>Bank-ſide</hi> near the <hi>Bear-Garden,</hi> in <hi>Southwark</hi> of the Palſie, who had not the uſe of his hands to cut his meat or to help himſelf not any manner of way for the ſpace of three years, and about two months, being near fourſcore years of age, and I ſoon made him well, with Gods help, and he hath the uſe of his hands as well as any of his age. <hi>Michael Smith</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Griffen</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> of great pains in his limbs and the Cramp. Mr <hi>Fawey</hi> at the <hi>Black Raven</hi> in <hi>Long-acre,</hi> of the Sciatica in his Hip. Mr. <hi>Thomas Day</hi> of <hi>Old-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Blue-anchor- alley,</hi> of a Fiſtula. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet Wheatley</hi> in <hi>Swan-alley</hi> in the <hi>Minories,</hi> of the Tooth-ach, and alſo of great pain in her Head and Ear. Mr. <hi>Bull</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Grove-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Hackney,</hi> of the third day Ague.</p>
            <p>I ſaid in my former book, that in regard my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> and <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms</hi> was counterfeited by ſo many Cheats, that it ſhould not be called by that name any more during the time of my book, but now I have made a new book, I have given it the ſame name again; now I have given you ſuch good notice of the Cheats, that I think you will be ſo wiſe as not to take any thing from any by this name, but what you have from my own hand that you may not be cheated of your money and your lives alſo. For they are things of my own Study and practiſe for many years therefore if any proffer ſuch things to ſell, and ſay they had them of me, believe them not, for it is Counterfeited. I will give you notice of one or two of theſe wicked fellows which doe indeavour to cheat you, I ſay to prevent your being poyſoned, for thoſe which Miniſter Phyſick without art, if they Cure one by chance they may kill above a hundred to every one, for it is with them as the Blind man hit the Hair: it was twelve or thirteen years before I could bring to paſs to miniſter things with ſafety to do good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though I both ſtudied and travelled hard, and practiſed continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon the worſt of Diſtempers in all bodys; which do make me admire the impudence of theſe wicked fellows, who do not at all value the lives of people, ſo they can but cheat them of their money. As one <hi>Bullin</hi> whom I took in out of the Streets and relieved him a whole Winter otherwiſe he had ſtarved. As alſo one <hi>Perry</hi> a Porter which I imployed to give out my books and to make clean the Streets before my Houſe, till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and diſquiet in my Family<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that I was fain to put him away; there are many others
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104840:3"/>me, for I bleſs God I have enough to maintain me and my Family: but for fear they ſhould poyſon any of the people before they are found out; therefore be ſure you take not any thing from any perſon in the name of <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> or <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms,</hi> but from my own hand, for I have given you but a hint of the Cheats, to what they are in number.</p>
            <p>Now I will ſet down ſome of the Cures which I have done in the Country, and firſt one great Cure with witneſſes to it, and here followeth a true Copy of the Certificate. He cured me <hi>John Aſteet</hi> of <hi>Totneſs</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von-Shire</hi> of the Stone in the Bladder, I being about Threeſcore years of age when he cured me, I was ſo bad that I was not able to make one drop of water, and my pain was ſo terrible that no tongue is able to expreſs, and he gave me a powder which in ſix hours time broke the Stone to pieces and brought it from me; and from this t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me my pain left me, and I could make water very well, and was not troubled any more with the Stone nor pain; In witneſs hereunto we have put our hands, <hi>John Aſtcot, John Sampſon, Peter Brag, Ptolomeus Sampſon, John Sampſon, Zach. Punchard, Anthony Lang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth, John Amat,</hi> 1668. this is a true Copy of the Certificate, and any that pleaſe may ſee the Certificate. <hi>Richard Pope</hi> of <hi>Brickham,</hi> two miles off <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> of great pain in his ſtomach, ſides and back. <hi>John Beard</hi> of <hi>Totneſs</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of lameneſs in all his Limbs, and ſoon made him lay by his Crutches. <hi>John Day</hi> of <hi>Churiton-Buſhel,</hi> nine miles from <hi>Exeter,</hi> of great pain in his head, with black Cataracts breeding in his Eyes, I helpt him of his pain of his head; and alſo the black Catharacts which were breeding in his Eyes, and made him ſee very well, though he was almoſt blind, and I did it without putting him to any pain, or putting any thing, into his Eyes. <hi>William Blackaller</hi> of <hi>Totneſs</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of the Apoplexy and Palfie on his right ſide, and a Conſumption withall, ſo that he could not riſe out of his bed, and none thought that ever he would recover, and I firſt made him able to go on Crutches, and ſoon after without, and within a reaſonable time with Gods help, recovered him. <hi>William Randal</hi> of <hi>Stook,</hi> three miles off <hi>Exeter,</hi> of the Megrim, with a Cough, and great pain at his ſtomack and back. <hi>Judeth Doabs,</hi> living near the South-gate in <hi>Exeter,</hi> at Mr. <hi>William Butlers,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs. <hi>William Friggy</hi> of <hi>Glaſton,</hi> four miles from <hi>Wells,</hi> of great pain in his ſide, being aged, and could not get help by any other. Miſtreſs <hi>Suſanna Butſon</hi> of <hi>Otery,</hi> five miles off <hi>Honington</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of the Convulſion Fits; the Fit uſed to take her every day, or every other day, and hold her twelve hours every Fit, and I took away her Fit in a quarter of an hour, and could not hear that ever ſhe was troubled any more therewith. <hi>Robert Brownſy</hi> of <hi>Honington</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of the Cough with pain and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in all his Body, and he made him able to go about his work in three or four days, with Gods help. <hi>Judeth Browiſie</hi> of the ſame Town, of the Collick and Spleen. <hi>Rebecca Phillips</hi> of the ſame Town, of a ſad pain in her Head and Breaſt, ſhe being near fourſcore years of age, and a very weak woman, and had made tryal of many, and ſpent much money to no purpoſe, and I gave her ſpeedy Remedy, with Gods help. <hi>Mary Wilſon</hi> of <hi>Buckeril</hi> Pariſh, two miles off <hi>Honington,</hi> of looſeneſs of her Teeth when they were ready to fall out of her head. <hi>Suſanna Woran</hi> of <hi>Stockland,</hi> ſive miles off <hi>Honington,</hi> of the Ague and Feaver. <hi>William Cook</hi> of <hi>Newton Abbot,</hi> of the Ague. Mr. <hi>Whelly</hi> of <hi>Wells,</hi> of Lameneſs, who was not able to riſe out of his bed. <hi>William Grigg</hi> of <hi>Atherford,</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of great pain and weakneſs, which was cauſed of a great Surſeit, and all that had him in hand had given him off for a dead man, and I gave him preſent eaſe, and cured him. <hi>John Farmer</hi>'s ſon of <hi>Riſon,</hi> a mile off <hi>Taunton,</hi> of the griping pains in the Guts. <hi>Walter Colins</hi> of <hi>Charlton Adam,</hi> eight miles off <hi>Tarnton,</hi> of Deafneſs, with noiſe and ſinging in his head, who could not get help in many years, being of great age when he was cured. And you ſhall hear of ſome of the great Cures I have done at <hi>Briſtol.</hi> I cured the wife of <hi>William Thomas</hi> in <hi>Cock-lare,</hi> going out of <hi>Corn-ſtreet</hi> to <hi>Nicholas-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of a Cancer in her left breft and ſide, when they which had her in hand gave her off for a dead woman, the Diſtemper being ſo bad with hardneſs of red, yellow, and black colours, which was very ſad to behold, and they every day put in a Tent between her Ribs quite into her body, about the length and bigneſs of a mans finger, ſo that I judge the end of the Tent muſt needs go within an inch of her heart; ſhe had alſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Feaver attending on her, ſo that there could not any thing be expected but death, I preſently cauſed the Tent to be laid by, and I never applied Tent nor Inſtrument, but gave her preſent eaſe, and cured her in about nine or ten weeks time, with Gods help. <hi>Benjamin Holut,</hi> living in <hi>Swan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> Court on the Kay in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of the Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd-days Ague, who could not get help in twelve or thirteen moneths. Mr. <hi>John Brooks</hi> his wife in the back lane without the Caſtle Gate in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of the Second days Ague and Feaver. <hi>Thomas Roads</hi> of <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud-Mead</hi> of the Priſick and Cough, with Conſumption, with an extraordinary great pain and ſtoppage at his ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mach. <hi>William Panchin</hi> near the ſign of the Leg in <hi>Temple-ſtreet</hi> of the Sciatica Gout in his hip, who was ſo lame therewith, that he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain to creep about the houſe on his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104840:3"/>age, and could not get help by any other, and I made him as well as ever he was in his life, with Gods help. <hi>Thomas Elot</hi> near the Leg in <hi>Temple-ſtreet</hi> of the Cough. <hi>John Doubting</hi> of <hi>Luence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mead</hi> of great weakneſs. <hi>Anne Doubting</hi> of the ſame place, being in great danger of Death with Feaver and Surfeit, and with Gods help I made her perfect well. <hi>William Day</hi> near the Grey-hound in <hi>Broud-Mead</hi> of Deafneſs, being near threeſcore years of age when he was cured, and I made him as well as ever he was in his life. <hi>William Andrews</hi> at the ſign of the Roſe without the Caſtle Gate of a ſad Bruiſe and an Impoſthume, who was ſo bad therewith, that he kept his bed, and was like to die of it, and I ſoon cured him. <hi>James Bramble</hi> of <hi>Downing</hi> in <hi>Maungerfield</hi> Pariſh, three miles from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of the Dropſie, with great pain and ſwellng over all his body, and I took away all pain and ſwelling, and made him as well as ever he was in his life. Mr. <hi>Kympton</hi>'s ſon of <hi>Rackly-ſtreet</hi> of the ſhaking Palſie in his head, ſhoulders, arms, hands, and ſeet; and I made him well in a ſhort time. I did much good to <hi>Deborah Philips</hi> over againſt the Three Kings in the ſame ſtreet for the Fits of the Mother, great pains in her ſtomach, and great weakneſs, who could not get help by any other. Miſtreſs <hi>Collins</hi> living near the Caſtle Gate of an Impoſthume in her Ear. Theſe are ſome of the Cures I did at <hi>Briſtol.</hi> Now you ſhall hear of ſome of the Cures I have done at <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Warminſter</hi> in <hi>Wiltsſhire</hi> and thereabouts. I cured <hi>John Stephens</hi> of <hi>Swanſwick</hi> two miles off <hi>Bath,</hi> of the Sciatica pain in his hip and ſide, being above threeſcore years of age. <hi>John Cox</hi> of <hi>Bath,</hi> of Lameneſs, who could not get help by any other. <hi>Benjamin Cot</hi> of <hi>Bath,</hi> of two ſad Ulcers in his foot. <hi>John Powel</hi> of <hi>Donker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> three miles off <hi>Bath,</hi> of a Wen in his Eye-brow, he being about thirty years of age, and brought the Wen into the world with him, and he cured him without cutting. <hi>Stephen Higgins</hi> his Child of <hi>Stockley</hi> near <hi>Caline</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> of the Rickets and Feaver. <hi>John Salmon</hi> of <hi>Marſhfield</hi> in <hi>Gleceſterſhire,</hi> of great pain and lameneſs in his ſhoulder. <hi>John Cryars</hi> ſon about a mile and a half from <hi>Bath,</hi> in the Road to <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of a broken belly. <hi>Robert Brothers</hi> of the <hi>Devizes-Green,</hi> of the Ague and Vomiting Blood. <hi>Elizabeth Gariſh</hi> of <hi>Worminſter,</hi> in <hi>VViltſhire</hi> of the Conſumption, with great pain at her ſtomach, head, and ſide, who could not get help by any other in three years. <hi>John Butcher</hi> of <hi>Hay-Grove,</hi> a little way out of <hi>VVorminſter</hi> of the Cancer in his ſhoulder, neck, and throat, when he was ſo bad, that none would meddle with him but my ſelf, and when I had undertaken him, the Doctors thereabouts laught; and one ſaid he would give me fifty pounds if I cured him, and others likewiſe; but when I had cured him, there was not any would give me a penny but himſelf; however with Gods help, I made him as well as ever he was in his life. <hi>William Davies</hi> his daughter of the ſame town, of the Evil in her neck. <hi>Elizabeth Bucher</hi> of the ſame town, of a Scald, or leprous head, who was twelve or thirteen years of age, and brought it into the world with her; I alſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her ſiſter of the ſame Diſtemper. <hi>John Sidinham</hi> of <hi>Chicklit,</hi> ſix miles off <hi>Worminſter,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Anne Fenny</hi> of <hi>Froom,</hi> five miles off <hi>Worminſter,</hi> of the Evil in her neck. <hi>Henry Bealing</hi> of <hi>Gillingham</hi> Pariſh, ſeven miles off <hi>Worminſter,</hi> of the Sciatica Gout in his hip and ſide, being about three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore years of age when he was cured. Theſe are ſome of the Cures which I have done at <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>VVorminſter</hi> in <hi>VViltſhire,</hi> and now you ſhall hear of ſome of the Cures I have done at <hi>Coventry.</hi> I cured Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> his daughter of <hi>Fillingſly</hi> three miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs. The wife of <hi>Robert Har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſon</hi> of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> a mile off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Conſumption, Feaver, Surfeit, Jaundie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yellow and black, having theſe five Diſtempers all on her at once, and all that had her in hand had given her off for a dead woman, and yet God was pleaſed to give a bleſſing to the means I uſed for her, and reſtored her to her former health again. <hi>William Hayght</hi> of <hi>Alſly</hi> pariſh a mile off <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry,</hi> of the Sciatica pain in his hip. <hi>Samuel Graviners</hi> ſon of <hi>Coventry,</hi> both the Bones of his Arm were broken and ſticked out through the skin and I made him as well as eve he was in his life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Elizabeth Weltons</hi> ſon of <hi>Hil-worton,</hi> ſix miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs. The Wife of <hi>Thomas Wemon</hi> of <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il,</hi> two miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Mother and Spleen. <hi>George Moris</hi> of <hi>Anſly,</hi> four miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Cancer on his Face, who could not get help in fourteen years, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near threeſcore years of age when he was cured. Theſe are ſome of the Cures I have done at <hi>Coventry,</hi> and now you ſhall hear of ſome of the Cures which I have done in <hi>Northampton-ſhire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arby-ſhire, Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham-ſhire</hi> and thereabouts. I cured Mr. <hi>Henry Chapman</hi> of <hi>Moulion,</hi> three miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> whoſe hand was to be cut off, and I cured him without the loſs of a Joynt. Mr. <hi>Francis Plowmans</hi> daughter of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> two miles off <hi>Northampton,</hi> of the Palſie, withered Hand and Arm. Mr. <hi>Vicars</hi> daughter of <hi>Little Oakley,</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs. <hi>John Smiths</hi> daughter of <hi>Northampton,</hi> of Convulſion Fits. The wife of <hi>William Lacke</hi> of <hi>Grunden,</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> of a Cancer in her neck. The wife of Mr. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> of <hi>Weſt-hadingham,</hi> ſeven miles off <hi>Northampton,</hi> of lameneſs in her back and hips, which came with Child-bearing, and I ſoon made her throw by her Crutches. <hi>Richard Kinds</hi> childe of <hi>Backwell</hi> near <hi>Litter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104840:4"/>ſtrength to ſtand, and I made the Childe able to go about the ſtreets in a formights time, with Gods help, <hi>William Rabet</hi> of <hi>Kettering</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Thomas Gonn</hi> of <hi>Redington,</hi> three miles off <hi>Northampton,</hi> of the third-day Ague. The wife of <hi>Robert Auſtin</hi> of <hi>Hitchin</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire,</hi> of a lame Leg and ſhrunk Sinews, who could not ſet her foot to the ground nor get help in twenty years, &amp; I made her as well as ever ſhe was in her life. <hi>John Smith</hi> of <hi>Kings Waldon</hi> three miles off <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of a Wen on his forehead, without any ſcar. <hi>Timothy Robinſon</hi> of <hi>Soothill</hi> pariſh near <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of the third-days Ague. <hi>Richard Dear</hi> of <hi>Shillington</hi> three miles off <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of Deafneſs. <hi>Peter Shadbolt</hi> of <hi>Graveriſt,</hi> four miles off <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Matthew Negus</hi> of St. <hi>Needs</hi> of the third-days Ague, who could not get help in three years. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn Reck</hi> of <hi>Swacy,</hi> three miles off St <hi>Ives,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Robert Thur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> of <hi>Hadinham</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> who had kept his bed a long time of Lameneſs with great pains, and could not get help by any, and I cured him in one weeks time, with Gods help. Mr. <hi>John Acton</hi> of <hi>Howbick Hall</hi> near <hi>Worksup</hi> in <hi>Notinghamſhire,</hi> who had been quite deaf above twenty years, being about fourſcore years of age, and I made him hear as well as any, in a month or ſix weeks time. <hi>Robert Pillings</hi> of <hi>Notingham,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Thomas Rainer</hi> of the ſame town, of ſix Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in his Leg, who could not get help in many years. The wife of <hi>William Biges</hi> a Smith in <hi>Darby,</hi> of the Mother and Spleen. <hi>Thomas Foſter</hi> of <hi>Darby,</hi> of the Scurvey all over his body. <hi>Mary T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mlins</hi> of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kuſten</hi> on the Hill near <hi>Darby,</hi> of the Evil in her hand. <hi>Margaret Vallance</hi> of <hi>Long-Moſton</hi> near <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rth</hi> in <hi>Darbyſhire,</hi> of the Evil in her Neck. Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> of <hi>Spaldock,</hi> three miles off St. <hi>Needs,</hi> of the Sciatica Gout, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an Lodſon</hi> of <hi>Southward</hi> near St. <hi>Needs,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe witneſſes I ſuppoſe are ſufficient (although I could produce many more) to aſcertain the truth, but to thoſe that will not be perſwaded from the mouths of ſo many witneſſes, it is altogether in vain to uſe any further Arguments. I know there are many perſons which make it their buſineſs to caſt an Odium upon me, but they are either ſuch as are of opinion that Phyſick is altogether unneceſſary, or ſuch as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the greateſt of Cures, but are indeed no better than meer Cheats; I deſire all good people to be ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wary how they truſt any ſuch Pretenders.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Cordial Vill,</hi> and <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms,</hi> is Counterfeited by ſo many Cheats that I was fain to change the names of them both, in my laſt book, but now they ſhall be called <hi>Jones</hi>'s <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms;</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi>'s <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> of <hi>Hatton Garden,</hi> three doors from the ſigne of the <hi>New-hole in the Wall,</hi> and three doors from the ſign of the <hi>Golde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ball,</hi> which cannot be had but from his own hand, and at his houſe as aforeſaid; therefore if any one proffer to ſell any thing by either of theſe names, as <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms,</hi> or <hi>Cordial Pill,</hi> then know that they are Cheats, and if you have any thing of this name of any of the Cheats, and that you come to any harme thereby; you ſhall blame your ſelves and not me, becauſe I have given you ſufficient warning, for if you have it from my own hand, it is as ſafe as a bit of bread.</p>
            <p>This my <hi>Balſom</hi> being taken from my own hand helps the Tetter, Ringworm, Shingles, or any ſorts of Worms in the Face, Noſe, Mouth, Teeth, and Gums, It helpeth the Tooth-ach, and faſteneth looſe Teeth, though they are ready to fall out; It will ſoon take away the Scurvies out of the Gums, and help any ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Mouth and Throat. It will help any ſort of Head-ach, and is preſent help for bleeding at the noſe if you put it up plentifully into that noſtrill that bleedeth, and hold it cloſe on to the ſide of the griffel of the Noſe where the vein is broken, and it helpeth preſently. For the Head-ach, anoint the Noſtrills, and Temples, but if you have not preſent eaſe by ſo doing anoint the Head where the pain is and in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I never knew it fail; for the Tooth-ach apply it to that Tooth and Gum that acheth with a little fine linne ragg and wear it as a plaiſter, and ſo faſt as the rheume waſheth it away put on another till the pain is gone, which is moſt commonly in leſs then a quarter of an hour; for looſe Teeth apply it as for the Tooth-ach, and wear the plaiſter all night, and it will not fail you: and for ſoreneſs in the Mouth, and foul Teeth you may anoint the Mouth, and for a fore Throat take as much as a ſmall Nutt every night going to bed. It doth help the Conſumption, and Cough, by taking the quantity of a ſmall Nut in the morning faſting, and laſt at night. It will help the Running of the Reines, Gonorrhea, weakneſs and waſting in the Back, and the heat &amp; waſting of the Kidneys and Reines by taking the quantity of a ſmall Nutt evening and morning, and drink ſix ſpoonfulls of red Wine or warm Milk after it, this kind of waſt is very dangerous, and you know it by a thin white cloud on the top of your Urine in the morning, or a bricky ſubſtance ſticking to the bottom and ſides of the pot. It will take away the Leproſie at two or three dreſſings though they bring it into the world with them, that is outwardly, but they muſt take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to take away the cauſe inwardly; for the Cramp, you muſt rub it well into the part grieved with your full hand, and it taketh it away preſently; and if you will help the ſhrinking ſinewes, you muſt wear it on the part grieved with a piece of thin bladder, to keep it ſoaking in, and ſometimes bath it well in with the heat of the fire. It doth not fail curing a Stinking Breath that proceedeth from the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and when you would not have any to ſmell your Breath rub a little of it up into your Noſtrills <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104840:4"/>the Stomach and Belly for three or four nights going to bed, it doth aſſwage the Bellies of Children which are ſwelled, and ſomtimes gently purgeth, if the Body be foul: but you muſt bath it well in with the heat of the fire; morning and evening, and lay a linnen cloth warm thereon; and ſo wear it for pains in the Stomach, ſides, and belly, you muſt chafe it well in with the heat of the fire, and then apply it with a piece of thin Bladder and ſo wear it; for the pain of the Back in like manner, only do not rub it in, but wear it as a plaiſter only: for the Piles and Hemorrhoids anoint the part grieved. It helpeth pains in the Feet, ſore Nails, or any dead fleſh that groweth thereon by applying it with a piece of thin bladder to keep it ſoaking in. It will Cure a new wound with a few dreſſings, though the Member be cut three parts off, if you take it quickly and bind it up plentifully with the <hi>Balſom,</hi> and renew it once in a day; and in a few days it will grow together again: it will help it a man be run through a Leg or Arm if it be taken at the firſt and applyed plentifully round the member grieved, &amp; renew it morning and evening: and for any ſort of old ſores, you muſt apply it as a plaiſter morning and evening, and it will cure though the bones be half rotted off, but you need not apply and tent with it not to any new or old ſores, take it upon my word, I do believe it is the beſt that ever was found out for old and new ſores both inward and outward if you have it from my own hand. It giveth comfortable reſt by anointing the Noſtrills and Temples going to bed, that is if the body be not very foul; it will diſſolve and cure hard kernels, and knobs that grow in the necks of boyes and girles without pain or breaking the skin. It taketh away red pimples, or any ſuch like Diſtemper in the face, killeth the black headed worms in the face and noſe, by anointing when you goe to bed, it giveth preſent help for any ſharp humour that breaketh out, but you muſt anoint for that but once in two or three days. It helpt Mr. <hi>Bailliff</hi> a Scrivener in <hi>Chippingham</hi> in <hi>Wilts-Shire</hi> of the ſhaking Palſie by applying it to the wriſts for three or four days, in ſo much that ſome Gentlemen of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey there abouts, would not believe till they had ſeen, but ſent for him and me alſo; and when they ſaw he could lift a glaſs of bear to his mouth without ſpilling, they believed becauſe they knew he had not any ſuch uſe of his hands of a long time before. However it hath done greater Cures ſince, for inſtance one Mr. <hi>Gregorie Coe</hi> living on the <hi>Banck ſide</hi> near the <hi>Bear-garden,</hi> of the Palſie, who had not the uſe of his hands to cut his meat for ſome years being near fourſcore years of age, and by the means of this my <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms</hi> he ſoon had good uſe of them. It did help Mr. <hi>Ward</hi> of <hi>Grunden</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton</hi> of the Palſie, when he was not able to turn in his bed, and no other means would doe him any good. I could mention many which have been Cured by applying my <hi>Balſom</hi> to the Member grieved, and it faileth not doing good for the Palſie; it will ſoon take away all pains from the ſhoulders, armes, hands, knees, ankles, and feet by applying it with a piece of thin bladder as aforeſaid. It helpeth any kind of ſore Breaſts; It did ſave and help the wife of Mr. <hi>Richard Yockney</hi> of <hi>Wall-Minſter</hi> in <hi>Wilts-Shire,</hi> when ſhe could not be delivered of her Child by any means, and ſo ſoon as they had applyed this <hi>Balſom,</hi> ſhe was preſently delivered of a live Child, with hundreds more which I might mention, and they all did well. It doth Cure any fleſhy Rupture by applying it to the part grieved, it giveth eaſe to children breeding Teeth by anointing the part grieved on the outſide. It helpeth thoſe whoſe limbs are waſting, and their fleſh withering away if they be not too far ſpent. It will give preſent eaſe for the Fiſtula in the Hip, or any other part of the Body, when no other means will doe any good, and will bring out the little pieces of rotted bones without paine. it Cureth and giveth preſent eaſe for all Burnings and Scaldings, and taketh away the pain ſo ſoon as laid to the part grieved. I have taken notice, that when I have ſcalded or burnt my finger, I have applyed my <hi>Balſom</hi> and it hath given eaſe of the pain ſo ſoon as I have laid it on, and taken out the fire in two or three hours, ſo it does in any kind of burning and ſcalding if it be not bliſtered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you lay it on; which if it be, it will require a little longer time. And for Surfits, want of Appetite, want of quiet Sleep, or any ſudden Diſtemper you may take as much as a ſmall Nutt going to bed, and you will find good for moſt Diſtempers, if it be taken when any Diſtemper firſt takes you, that is if you have it from my own hand, but if you have it of any of the Cheats though they ſay 'tis my <hi>Balſom</hi> you may chance to come too ſhort home, but you ſhall not blame me; It will cure all Squats and Bruiſes, Strains in the Back or any part of the Body, or thoſe that get Strains with over lifting, I do believe that if it were poſſible for a man to live and practice with it one hundred years, that one might make it cure all diſeaſes both inward and outward. I ſell it in pots one ounce for a ſhilling, and they that have a pound together have it cheaper, it will laſt good fourty years, it is good Merchandize in other Countreys, and I believe thoſe that take this and my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> with them upon that account, muſt needs get twenty for one, With this <hi>Balſom</hi> I do cure Limbs which the bones are rotte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome half off, and ſome the bones quite off, and any that leaſe may ſee the rotted bones and the parties cured.</p>
            <p>I never heard that the Cheats did ever give any Books before I came to <hi>London</hi> and gave out my Books, but now many of them make Books like my former Book, and there tell you a fine ſtory of a Cock &amp; a Bul, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104840:5"/>them one from the other but by their works, he that cheats you will pleaſe you better in words than he that deals honeſtly, but where are the Cures they have done all this while, have they practiſed ſo long and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did one Cure; ſurely they are unfortunate Phyſitians that are not able to ſpeak of one Cure they have done, it may be they will tell you a lye and ſhow you a reaſon for it, ſay they will not ſpeak of the Cures they have done for ſome good reaſon, but ſay they we could put the names of hundreds in our Books but will not; but if you will know the right truth why they doe not put the names of ſome in their Books becauſe they never cured any body, and that is the true reaſon why they put none into their Books, there is not any man that giveth a Book let him pretend what he will, that if he had ever done any Cures, but he would have ſet down ſome of the names of them in his Books, therefore let them not try experience on your bodys, but find out ſuch as are known to do great Cures, make uſe of them; and let not theſe young Doctors practice on your bodys, for fear you loſe your money and your lives alſo. Pray inquire of the Cures I have done, they that are honeſt will ſpeak the truth.</p>
            <p>Now I will ſet down ſome of the virtues of my <hi>Cordial Pill,</hi> for I think in regard I have told you ſo often in my former Book how the Cheats do counterfeit it, that you are ſatisfied not to buy any but what you have from my own hand, and if you have it from my own hand it helpeth any ſort of ſore and Rheumie Eyes though never ſo bad, all ſwellings in the Face lips and noſe, it helpeth Melancholy and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Spirits, it did help Mr. <hi>Withers</hi> of Melancholy, who was ſo bad that he could not go about any buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a ſmall quantity of it made him as well as ever he was in his life; the people of the <hi>Goat</hi> Tabern over againſt the <hi>Sheep-pens</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> can give you a farther account of this great Cure. It will help thoſe which are Mad, or through abundance of Melancholy are grown fooliſh, it expelleth wind upward and downward, and ſtrengtheneth the Stomach, cleanſeth the Head, Stomach, Kidneys, Reins and Bladder of all touch ſlimie Humors which nature is not able to carry away; and all ſharp humours which breed Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or Kankers in the mouth, and at the root of the Tongue, which you may ſee when they are breeding if you draw forth the tongue a little way ſide-ways, then you may ſee the tongue will be a little raw on both ſides near the throat, then is the Blood throughout all the whole Body corrupted: this Diſtemper moſt commonly breedeth without pain, &amp; that is the reaſon ſo many die of it, becauſe they ſeek not for help till it is too late, but when it doth begin to be painfull, they are almoſt paſt Cure, becauſe the Blood is all Aduſt. This Diſtemper is very dangerous and cauſeth many a terrible death, it is cauſed by a ſharp humour that diſtilleth down from the Brain, and this <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> dryeth and carrieth away all ſuch ſharp and mixed humors which breed this Diſtemper, which to the beſt of my knowledge there is not any thing in the world like it, for taking away ſuch humors, for it is continully drawing of all tough ſlimie humours from all parts of the body which no other Medicine will or can reach, and it doth it by its gentle and mild ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; for if you eat as much as a ſmall Nut of it in the morning faſting before you goe about your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you ſhall ſeldom hear any more of it till ſix or eight hours after, and then it may give you two or three ſtools; and not gripe nor diſtemper you in all this time: and if you take a like quantity when you goe to bed, it will doe the like in the morning; and note that whatſoever humour oriendeth it bringeth it off, as in ſome it bringeth away green Choler, in another black Choler, and in another yellow Choler, and in another thin watry humours mixed with yellow and black, and ſometimes mixed with green according as they are gendred in the body, and it is ſuch a friend to Nature, that they joyn hand in hand to drive out all theſe ſharp and mixed humours out of the body. Nature rejoyceth when it is received into the body, as you may ſee by the party that taketh it will be more chearfull and lightſom by far than at any other time, it doth correct the ſharpneſs of all tough ſlimie humours, and draweth them back out of the Veins and Arteries to the Stomach, and ſo ſends them away down through the Bowels, and ſo by that means it leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not any foul corner of the body unſwept, and reaſon will tell you that if three or four ounces of it will cure ſuch a diſtemper of Melancholy as you read of before, that there can but few diſtempers come amiſs but what it doth good for, and them I ſhall name at the latter end; and you know it is but two ſhillings the ounce, and that ſerveth ten or twelve times taking and hinders no buſineſs, and reaſon will alſo tell you, that if it will carry off ſuch tough ſharp mixed humours, it muſt needs take away the Scurvy out of the body both Root and Branch, and the Dropſie and all other diſtempers that joyneth with it, and reaſon may tell you alſo, that if it draweth away all this vicious matter out of the Veins and Arteries, that it muſt needs free the Liver and Spleen of all obſtructions, and ſo by that means helpeth the Fits of the Mother and Spleen, and all other diſtempers which are cauſed by that obſtruction: and you may underſtand that by the drawing away this vicious matter out of the Veins and Arteries it muſt need cleanſe the whole maſs of Blood to the purpoſe, and by that means help the Gonorrhea, running of the Reins, and waſting weakneſs in the Back, Kidneys, and dryeth up all Venerial diſtempers, and reſtoreth to ſtrength; it doth ſo much cleanſe the blood of all melancholy, that in young people it changes the colour of the black and ſwarthy skin, it is good for them that are well to take it Spring and Fall to preſerve health, for it will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104840:5"/>her Blood and cauſes good and wholſom Milk, for the Milk is bred of her Blood, and ſometimes her Blood being hot and foul cauſeth the Child to be ſickly and cannot goe to ſtool but ſeldom; this being taken a little now and then as aforeſaid will keep her Milk in good order, and the Childs body alſo; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it doth draw away all tough ſlimie humours out of the Veins and Arteries, reaſon will tell you that it is ſuch humours which breedeth the Stone, Sand and Gravil in the Kidneys, Reins and Bladder, and therefore by taking away thoſe humours muſt needs prevent the breeding of the Stone, and alſo the Sand and Gravil; It will not help the Conſumption, nor no ſort of Feaver, nor the Jaundies, nor the Gripes, nor looſneſs; but for any other diſtemper there is hardly any but it doth good for it. A Man or a Woman may take as much as a ſmall Nut morning and evening if their bodies are hard to work on, but others that are eaſie to work may take of it once a day as much as a ſmall Nut in the morning before you goe forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your buſineſs; and it will give you two or three ſtools in the afternoon, and if you take the ſame quantity going to bed it will doe the like in the morning; and for Children give them a little bit according to their age and ſtrength, and diſſolve it in any liquid thing the Child will take it in; it hath a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant taſte, and you may eat it as you eat bread, or roul it in little balls, or diſſolve it in any thing any way ſo it goeth into the body, it will doe its work; you cannot err in giving it to Children, for it is as ſafe as a bit of bread. I ſell it for two ſhillings the ounce, and one ounce will ſerve ten or twelve times taking for a Man or Woman, and for a Child or young People it will ſerve many times. This my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> and my <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms</hi> laſteth good fourty years, the older the better if you keep it cloſe covered; and any which goes to Sea, or into any other Countrey which taketh a good quantity of it together, I will uſe them ſo well, and ſet them in ſuch a way, that it ſhall be the beſt Merchandiſe they can carry with them. It cannot be had but from my own hands, therefore when the Cheats ſay they have it, or proffer it to ſell, believe them not, nor take any of their things for fear they cheat you of your money and your lives alſo. And note that violent purges cannot carry off ſuch ſharp and mixed humours, becauſe they goe ſpeedily through the body and leave the diſtemper behind, and make the body weak to little purpoſe. Now this my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> is alwaies gently drawing it away night and day &amp; weakens not the body nor hinders labor.</p>
            <p>I have another ſort of <hi>Balſom</hi> which is taken inward onely for ulcerated Gonorrhea, it giveth eaſe for that and for Ulcers in the Bladder and Kidneys, and preſently taketh away the ſharpneſs of Urine, and helps difficulty in making water. It doth cauſe a freſh lively colour in the Face, and cheareth the Spirits ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, it muſt be taken as much as a ſmall Nut every morning faſting; I ſell it for Five ſhillings the Ounce, and that will ſerve ten or twelve times taking.</p>
            <p>I have a white <hi>Balſom</hi> which I ſell for One ſhilling ſix pence the Ounce, which is taken inward for ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Breath, &amp; Ptiſick, it muſt be taken as much as a ſmall Nut morning and evening mixed well with powder of white Sugar Candy.</p>
            <p>I have two ſorts of <hi>Pills</hi> for the Ague, and Feaver, and you muſt take but one at the time of the Fit of neither ſort. The one is for the ordinary ſort of people, ſuch as are willing to follow their buſineſs when the fit is on them, about the middle of the cold fit you may take this little <hi>Pill,</hi> whether you are riding, walking, or about any other buſineſs, ſo you do not ſleep till the hot &amp; cold fits are both clear of you, for if you ſleep before the hot and cold fits are clear of you it will come again the next time as bad as before but thoſe which have not ſlept in the fit, I have known it cure ſome the firſt time, ſome the ſecond, and ſome the third, but I never knew any but it abated the Ague and Feaver at the firſt taking. I can affore to cure any ſuch for a crown, and not hinder any buſineſs, it doth not purge nor vomit nor diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the body any manner of way.</p>
            <p>The other is for ſuch as cannot work or be not able to work, which muſt be taken and goe to bed, may be given to children of any Age, as well as older people, this and the former are both as ſafe as a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of bread, and do not diſtemper the body, neither do they fail doing good. I never put this in print but now of late, and I make no queſtion but it will be counterfeited as well as my other things ſo ſoon as the Cheats get this Book of mine, I believe there are thouſands in and about <hi>London,</hi> which live upon nothing elſe but ſuch Roguerie.</p>
            <p>I have a Powder that helpeth thoſe whoſe fleſh waxeth ſoft and flaggie, which is the beginning of a Conſumption, which you may know by theſe ſignes, they will not eat their meat with ſo good an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite as formerly, they will have ſome times a ſmall husking cough, a tickling in the throat, their ſleep many times troubleſome, the body beginneth to grow weak, and they have nothing near the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of any thing in this world as they had formerly. This Powder helpeth all theſe diſtempers, if you take it, before you are too far ſpent. This Powder is for fine delicate tender bodies, ſuch as cannot take my <hi>Balſom</hi> inward, it hath a pleaſant taſte. I ſell it for five ſhillings the Ounce, and that will ſerve a Man or a Woman about three weeks, and it will ſerve little Children ſome ſix, eight, ten weeks according to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> It is a very rich <hi>Cordial,</hi> and doth not diſtemper the Body, you ſhall have a Note of directions with</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104840:6"/>
            <p>I make a Water that infallibly cureth the Sciatica pain in the Hip, if the Bone be not out, the pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is five ſhillings the two quarts, and moſt commonly that quantity doth the work, in two or three dreſſings</p>
            <p>I have a powder that doth often breake the Stone in the Bladder, and bringeth it away in Sand &amp; Gravil, the price is half a Crown the Ounce, a Man or a Woman may take as much as will lie upon a ſhilling in a draught of <hi>White-VVine</hi> every morning and evening, and for Children as much as will lie on a two pence, a groat, ſixpence, you cannot err in giving it, it is ſo ſafe.</p>
            <p>THE laſt thing though ſmall in quantity yet it doth good, according as it is here ſet down, as I have found by mine own Experience. It giveth preſent eaſe and comfort to a diſquiet mind and wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring diſpairing thoughts, which is as bad a Diſtemper as any is. It ſtrengtheneth the Memory exceedingly, and ſometimes recovereth the Senſes loſt. It drieth up all manner of Rhume which diſtilleth down from the Head, which doth many times breed Ulcers in the Mouth, in the Lunges, and Cancers in the Throat, and alſo a Conſumpt on and Cough. It taketh away this Rhume though never ſo ſharp, it abateth it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an hours time, it ſtrengthens the Stomach, purgeth Wind downwards Twenty four hours every time you take it. That is, if there be Wind in the Body that doth offend. It helpeth Vapors which aſcend from the Mother and Spleen, to the Head, which make ſome Women by Fits as if they had loſt part of their Senſes. It doth help Swimming in the Head and Swouning fits. It helpeth the Dropſie and Scurvie when theſe two Humors are mixed together and hard to be parted. It doth help ſower Belches, and cauſeth a good Appetite, the obſtruction of the Liver and Spleen, Agues and Feavers of all ſorts. It preſently helpeth Vomiting. And giveth preſent eaſe for the Griping pains of the Guts, and in a few times taking it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a Cure, as it may be witneſſed by Mr. <hi>Ward</hi> of Biſhop's head Court in <hi>Gray's-Inn-lane,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Michill</hi> of Angel alley in the ſame Lane, for himſelf and daughter, with Thouſands more which are bound to bleſs God for the ſpeedy Comfort they have found by this thing: the Wind-Collick, and Strangurie and pains in the Bladder. It doth preſently help bleeding by Urine or Stooll, the Jaundies yellow and black; the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Spleen, Running paines in the Joints. It doth preſerve Women from miſcarrying: what I ſay of it, is of a real truth, and it is as ſafe to take as a bit of Bread, and doth not Purge, nor Vomit, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper the Body any manner of way but giveth eaſe in moſt Diſtempers in about an hours time, with the bleſſing of God: and for the pain of the Collick, if it be of Wind, Sand, Gravel, or tough Slimie humors, it doth give preſent eaſe as aforeſaid: It doth commonly bring away Stones as bigg as Peaſe, and abundance of Gravel from Men and Women: what I have ſpoken of this thing is true for I have proved it for many years. It helpeth the Rickets in Children and ſuch as are troubled with Ptiſick, Cough, or Conſumption, and pining away with loſs of their fleſh, if they be not too far ſpent, it will ſoon recover them, it is no matter what age they are; I have helpt hundreds ſince my coming to <hi>London;</hi> as you may read of ſome of their names in this Book which were pined away to skin and bones, and done it in a ſhort time with ſmall charge.</p>
            <p>I cure all ſorts of Blindneſs or any Diſtemper in the Eyes, (ſo far as curable,) without pain or putting any thing into them, and take away the cauſes thereof, ſo that they are not troubled any more there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: therefore I adviſe you not to put any thing at all into your Eyes, for that never taketh away the cauſe, neither can it cure but cauſeth much pain, and many times putteth the Eyes out, or at leaſt maketh them paſt cure; then for you that ever intend to have cure, put not any thing at all into your Eyes.</p>
            <p>I cure any ſort of Burſtneſs in Men, Women and Children, and keep a Truſs-maker on purpoſe to make Truſſes for them; otherwaies they cannot be cured.</p>
            <p>I cure any ſort of Deafneſs provided it came not with blows, the ſound of Bells, the ſhooting off Guns, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Organ of the Ear be not fallen together, then you may have cure without pain.</p>
            <p>I cure any ſort of old rotten ſores with my <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms</hi> though the Bones be quite rotted off, and will have nothing till I have done if we agree for the Cure. It may be ſome Faithleſs people will ſay this cannot be true, but I think reaſon may tell you, that a man having travelled long and ſtill practiſed on the worſt of Diſtempers, may be better able to help Diſtempers than thoſe that have alwaies liv'd at home. And as for the ſaying I cure ſuch Members which the Bones are rotted off, if you pleaſe to come to my houſe you may ſee both the Bones and the parties cured; and for any Diſtemper I take in hand I will have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing till I have done, if it be a coſtly Cure and viſible.</p>
            <p>I cure the Scald or Leproſie-head, without pain or loſs of a hair of the head, as you may read among the cures you will find where I have done the like. I have preſent help for ſuch as cannot make water but with great pain, and take away all ſharpneſs of Urine though never ſo bad and give preſent eaſe. I cure all ſorts of Wens without cutting; or any other ſort of Tumor let it be what it will. I cure Convulſions, Falling-fickneſs, and Fits of the Mother, Dropſie and Timpany, Conſumption, and Cough in ſuch as are almoſt at Deaths-door, the Jaundies yellow and black, the Evil of any ſort, the Cancer, Wolf, Fiſtula, the Ague and Feaver, all pains in the Head though it be Megrim, Vertigo, Lethargies, or Apoplexies pains in the Shoulders, Arms, Stomach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104840:6"/>
            <p>And as for the Diſtemper which is the Plague in the Guts, I deſire you will not flatter your ſelves, ſo, there is not one of a hundred that ever wears it out without the uſe of means, but in moſt of thoſe which it doth not kill at the firſt, it goeth away and comes again, and then leaves them a little and comes again; and ſo lingers them out and brings them into a Conſumption and kills them at laſt, but all that come to me for this Diſtemper I give them preſent eaſe of pain, and abate the Diſtemper in an hours time; and cure them in a ſhort time, if you come or ſend before it is too late. I cure for a ſmall matter, I would not have any to be ſo fooliſh as to queſtion the truth hereof, ſeeing you have the names of ſo many witneſſes ſet down in this Book which I have already cured, their names and places where they live round about you, and you will find it as true as I ſay, and if there be any cure for you, you ſhall have it ſpeedily and for ſmall charge.</p>
            <p>I ſhould not need to have ſpoke ſo much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that I find the people ſome of them very faithleſs; and I ſuppoſe that is becauſe the Cheats have guld them of their money, therefore I adviſe you not to make uſe of every one alike, but diligently to enquire for him that is known to do great Cures, for by ſuch means you may have help, for he knows preſently what good can be done for you, and doe you good if poſſible there be any help, but thoſe that have practiſed but a little while, they muſt practiſe on your bodies ſeven and ſeven years, before they can have the experience to do Cures. I have had ſeveral times in my travells ten or twenty pounds for a Cure, after the Women and other Unskillfull perſons have done with it, which if they had gone to an able Phyſician at the firſt might have had help for a crown; or it may be leſs, but there are ſo many of theſe young Doctors in every corner, that no ſooner any perſon falls into any Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but they are ready at hand, and will undertake the Cure preſently, there they podder with their ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries till they have either killed them, or made them paſt Cure, and if they cure one by chance, though they kill hundreds afterward they will ſay their times were come, and in this manner Thouſands of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort of people loſe their lives; the truth is Millions of people are bound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to curſe all that practiſe on peples bodies without art, for Phyſick is a very dangerous thing for unskilfull people to meddle with.</p>
            <p>There are alſo ſome Women that ſo ſoon as their Husbands, or Children are ſick, will of their own heads, or by the advice of ſome ſilly Women, take upon them to Miniſter things to their own, and all for cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and ſo ſend them to their long home many times: pray God the blood of ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Husbands and Children may not belayd to their charge becauſe they know not what they doe.</p>
            <p>There are ſome Men and Women becauſe their friend doth practiſe Phyſick they will make uſe of none but him, it is true my friend will doe what he can for me, but when my life is gone my friend cannot help me to it again, therefore if I hear of any that have more skill than my friend, I will make uſe of him; and yet love my friend well, but my life better.</p>
            <p>Many of the people before they are helpt when they lye in great miſery, Oh! what they would give ſo eaſe, but when I have made them well, they ſay ſurely it was but a ſmall Diſtemper, becauſe he did it wit ſo ſmall a matter and for ſo little money.</p>
            <p>I helpt the wife of Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Golden Patton</hi> over againſt the <hi>Kings-bench</hi> in <hi>South wark</hi> of the Dropſie, who had loſt the greateſt part of her blood, ſo that ſhe had little or nothing left i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Veins but watry humours which turned to a ſad Dropſie with great weakneſs, and this came with miſcariage of two Children at one birth.</p>
            <p>I cured Mr. <hi>John Cherſly,</hi> living at the Sign of the <hi>Swan</hi> and <hi>Key</hi> in <hi>Brick-lane</hi> in <hi>Old-ſtreet,</hi> who had bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Deaf and troubled with great noiſe in his Head about forty years, he was quite Deaf, and threeſcore an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeventeen years of age whom I cured him; both he and his wife retourned thanks both to God and me, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he Heareth very well. Mr. <hi>William Shearman</hi> in <hi>Black Fryers</hi> over againſt the <hi>Dark entry,</hi> of the Stone an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gravel in the Kidneys and Eladder, and of the Sciatica pain in his Hip, and I helpt him in a fourtnights time with Gods help two years ſince, and cannot hear that he was troubled any more therewith.</p>
            <p>I cure all Fiſtulaes and Ulcers though the Bones be potted off, and you may chooſe whether you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it or no, but it is true.</p>
            <p>I helpt Mr. <hi>Ralph-Steel</hi> of <hi>Clarkenwell</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Flying-horſe,</hi> of a Conſumption and great weakneſs. Now if I ſhould adviſe you to have of my Balſom of Balſoms and keep it in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the houſe it may be you would ſay I ſpeak for my own ends to ſell my Balſom. I ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no, do not, for it is but one ſhilling the ounce, and it is ready if you ſhould have a Burn, a Scald, or Squat, a Bruiſe, a traine, a Cut, or any other miſchance, which will come in families, and you may look for them every day, and when any of theſe diſtempers comes, and having nothing to apply ſo ſoon as it is hurt, it runs on till it doth coſt a Crown or an Angel the cure, and ſometimes loſe the uſe of a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or a joint, after you have indured ſo much pain and miſery. This my Balſom taketh away the pain of a Burn or Scald, ſo ſoon as laid to the part grieved, and Cureth without Scar, they which know the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104840:7"/>
            <p>I helpt the Wife of Mr. <hi>Olive</hi> at the ſign of the Cock going in to the Market place in Newgate Market, of the Stone and Gravil, when ſhe was very bad indeed.</p>
            <p>The Cheats and their relations will ſay he is a Mountibank why will you go to him, but I ſay if I am Mountibank where is my Stage, why do they belye me.</p>
            <p>You may have more good of me for a Crown, or an Angel, then you can have at any other place for fourty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>I cured the wife of Mr. <hi>Iſaiah Palmer</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Old-Shears</hi> in <hi>Great VVood-ſtreet</hi> of a cancered Wen on her hand which was breeding about twelve years. The Daughter of Mr. <hi>Miradith</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Five Bells</hi> in <hi>Greys-Inn-lane,</hi> of the Feaver with gripes of the Guts. The Daughther of Mr. <hi>Bignall</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>VVhite-horſe</hi> near <hi>York-houſe</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> of the Evil in her Neck. The Daughter of Mr. <hi>Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondaſhim Pickis</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Seven-Starrs</hi> in <hi>Long-Acre,</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr <hi>Seal</hi> at the <hi>Soap-box</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> of the Feaver and gripes of the Guts. Mr. <hi>John Hayes</hi>'s ſon of <hi>Crown Court,</hi> in <hi>Baldwins-gardens,</hi> of a lame Arm who had no uſe of it, and I made him as well as ever he was in his life.</p>
            <p>I cured the Child of Mr. <hi>John Sarrit</hi> living at the upper end of <hi>Sea-alley</hi> in <hi>Kings-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> being pined away with a Conſumption to skin and bones, being above two years of age and could not bear any ſtrength to ſtand, and people thought it was unpoſſible for that Child to be recovered, however with Gods bleſſing he is grown as brave a lively Boy as any about <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I helpt the Child of Mr. <hi>John Scott</hi> of Roſe-alley in Golden-lane of the Convulſions and the evil in his eyes. The daughter of Mrs. <hi>Mary VVhite</hi> at the end of Bow-ſtreet in Bloomsbury the next door to the ſign of the Globe of the Evil in her eyes, the daughter of Mr. <hi>Standbridge</hi> in Catherine-wheele-yard over againſt the Sheep Pens in Smithfield of the Fever, with Gripes in the Guts Mrs. <hi>Margaret Guiny</hi> of Church-yard-Alley in Chick Lane, of great pain at her Stomack and back, and Vomating, Mr. <hi>Barnes</hi> of Hornſie fout miles from London of the Ague, the ſon of Mr. <hi>Keytte</hi> of Catherine-wheele-yard in Smithfield of the Comſuming ſever which is the worſt of Conſumptions.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Mary Rodgers,</hi> of <hi>Harp-ally</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> of the Feaver and Gripes of the Guts, when ſhe lay ſo weak that none thought ſhe would have lived, I cured her at the <hi>Golden-Cok</hi> in <hi>Shooe-lane,</hi> where I cured <hi>Mary Cox</hi> alſo of the ſame Diſtemper; the Chid of <hi>Theophilus Farmer,</hi> of <hi>Harts-horn-lane,</hi> near the Sign of the <hi>Plow,</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> near <hi>Northumberland-houſe,</hi> of the Rickers, who was two years old and a half, and could not bear any ſtrength to ſtand, and pined away to skin and bones, and I made him able, with God's help, to goe about the houſe by hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by things, and hath Fleſh grown ever his Bones again; the Daughter of Mr. <hi>Ryce,</hi> of <hi>Thiſtloworth,</hi> about ten miles from <hi>London,</hi> of a Weny tumor which grew into the Sinews upon the Joint between the Hand and the Arm, which grew up very hard, and fixed in the Sinews, and I cured her without hurting the Veins and Sinews.</p>
            <p>I would advize all thoſe that have unfortunately taken <hi>Mercury,</hi> and that it hath not all workt it ſelf out of the Body, which you may know by little pricking P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins in the Head and Noſe and other parts of the Body, with great Weakneſs, I have a Pill which will fetch it out though it hath lain never ſo long in the Body, and not hinder any Buſineſs; I have proved it by hundreds within theſe two years, and it never failed me.</p>
            <p>If any forbear coming to me for fear their Names ſhould be publiſhed when they are cured, I do aſſure them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ey ſhall not, for indeed my Book is already full of Witneſſes which are ſufficient to evidence the Truth.</p>
            <p>YOu are earneſtly deſired to communicate this Book to your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Friends, which may be a means of much good to them and many others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may ſpeak with me from</hi> 9 <hi>of the Clock in the Morning, till</hi> 5 <hi>in the Afternoon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104840:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
